Inventory of the Austria (Territory under Allied Occupation, 1945-1955) Records, 1946-1952
Hoover Institution Archives
Austria (Territory under Allied Occupation, 1945-1955) Records, 1946-1952
80199
Austria (Territory under Allied Occupation, 1945-1955)
8 manuscript boxes (3.0 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The records relate to civilian relief efforts, economic conditions, housing, and denazification in Austria after World War II, including minutes, reports, memoranda, statistics, laws, and bulletins.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955) Records, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
In 1938 the First Austrian Republic became part of Nazi Germany through an enforced annexation, the Anschluss. The Moscow Declaration of 1943 declared the Anschluss null and void restoring an independent Austrian state, one of aims of the Allies. Karl Renner formed a Provisional Government in late April 1945 and separated Austria from Germany by declaration. Following the end of hostilities, the provisional government was quickly recognized.
However, like Germany, Austria was divided into four zones by the Allies: American, British, French and Soviet. Vienna, being the capital, was similarly divided, though at its center was an International Zone which alternated sovereignty between the Four Powers at regular intervals. The European Advisory Commission agreed that Allied control in Austria should consist of an Allied Council, an Executive Committee, and staffs appointed by the four governments concerned.
Known as the Allied Commission for Austria, the purpose, as laid down by the European Advisory Commission, included the separation of Austria from Germany, the establishment of a central Austrian administration, preparation for the establishment of a freely elected Austrian Government, and facilitation of the administration of Austria. The commission for Austria was dismantled following the conclusion of the Austrian State Treaty on May 15, 1955.
Scope and Content of Collection
The records relate to civilian relief efforts, economic conditions, housing, denazification, democratization, demilitarization, and reparation for Austria after World War II and in Austria after World War II, including minutes, reports, memoranda, statistics, laws, and bulletins.
The collection represents materials documenting the efforts of economic rehabilitation of Austria under Allied Commission for Austria in 1946-1952 and contains documentation of the Office of Allied Council (ALCO) and Executive Committee (EXCO).
Materials also include documentation of the Military Government of Austria, the Headquarters United States Forces for Austria, and the United States High Commissioner U.S. Element Allied Commission for Austria.
The records are arranged as originally received from the organization; generally by Office of the Allied Administration of Occupied Austria.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Austria-History--Allied occupation, 1945-1955.
Collection Contents
- Allied Commission for Austria, 1946-1952; 1-8 (Box 1-8)
  - Allied Council, 1947-1952 (Folder 1-4)
    - Agenda, 1947-1949 (Folder 1: 1-2)
    - Minutes, 1947-1952 (Folder 1: 3-13)
    - Minutes, 1947-1952 (contd.) (Folder 2: 1-11)
    - Minutes, 1947-1952 (contd.) (Folder 3: 1-11)
    - Papers, 1947-1949 (Folder 3: 12-15)
    - Papers, 1947-1949 (contd.) (Folder 4: 1-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1947-1950 (Folder 4-7)
    - Agenda, 1947-1950 (Folder 4: 11)
    - Papers, 1948-1950 (Folder 4: 12)
    - Papers, 1948-1950 (contd.) (Folder 5: 1-11)
    - Papers, 1948-1950 (contd.) (Folder 6: 1-3)
    - Minutes, 1947-1950 (Folder 6: 4-11)
    - Minutes, 1947-1950 (contd.) (Folder 7: 1-7)
  - Gazette of the Allied Commission for Austria, nos. 72-84, Vienna, November 1951 - November 1952 (Folder 7: 8-11)
  - Military Government of Austria, handbook, vol. 1-2, issued 31 July 1946 (Folder 8: 1-2)
  - Civil Affairs, Austria, "Statistical Annex, Issue No. IV," to the Report of the United States High Commissioner, no date (Folder 8: 3)
  - Report of the United States High Commissioner, U.S. Element Allied Commission for Austria, no. 47, September 1949 (Folder 8: 4)
  - Headquarters United States Forces for Austria, APO 777, U.S. Army, reports, 1948-1949 (Folder 8: 4-5)